<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://waleedk2000.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://waleedk2000.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-01-08T15:04:46+05:00</updated><id>https://waleedk2000.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Waleed Kayani</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Overview of Cyber Security Legislations and Policies in Pakistan</title><link href="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Overview-of-CyberSecurity-Policies-in-Pakistan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overview of Cyber Security Legislations and Policies in Pakistan"/><published>2022-12-28T18:33:16+05:00</published><updated>2022-12-28T18:33:16+05:00</updated><id>https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Overview-of-CyberSecurity-Policies-in-Pakistan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Overview-of-CyberSecurity-Policies-in-Pakistan/"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote most of this content for an assignment. I think its very informative so i thought i would make a post about it on my blog here.</p> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Till date government of Pakistan has implemented three legislations and introduced one policy regarding information and cyber security. Legislations define many different crimes and their punishments.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://khalidzafar.com/wp-content/files_mf/1527082675ElectronicTransactionOrdiancne2002.pdf">Electronic Transaction Ordinance (ETO) 2002</a></li> <li><a href="http://pklegal.org/pdf/Prevention-of-Electronic-Crimes-Ordinance-2007-(PECO2007).pdf">Prevention of electronic crimes Ordinance, 2007</a></li> <li><a href="http://nasirlawsite.com/laws/peca1.htm">Prevention of Electronic Crimes Act (PECA) 2016</a></li> <li><a href="https://moitt.gov.pk/SiteImage/Misc/files/National%20Cyber%20Security%20Policy%202021%20Final.pdf">National Cyber Security Policy, 2021</a></li> </ul> <p>You can read in detail about these legislations and policies by clicking on them.</p> <h2 id="electronic-transaction-ordinance-eto-2002">Electronic Transaction Ordinance (ETO), 2002</h2> <p>This ordinance was passed in 2002 by the president of Pakistan. This was the first cyber related legislation in the country. This ordinance enabled the legal justice system of Pakistan to recognize electronic evidence and provided recognition of electronic signatures. Furthermore, it established a certification council and defined its functions and its members. The certification council deals with website certifications. However, the most important point this bill covers is the electronic offenses.</p> <p>The bill defines punishments of crimes such as:</p> <ul> <li>False information to certification authorities</li> <li>Issuance of false certification</li> <li>Violation of privacy of information</li> <li>Damage to information system</li> </ul> <h2 id="prevention-of-electronic-crimes-ordinance-2007">Prevention of Electronic Crimes Ordinance, 2007</h2> <p>This being the second IT related legislation was passed by President of Pakistan in 2007. The purpose of this ordinance is “to make provision for prevention of the electronic crimes” (Goverment of Pakistan, 2007). It covers the following offences:</p> <ul> <li>Criminal Access</li> <li>Criminal Data Access</li> <li>Data Damage</li> <li>System Damage</li> <li>Electronic Fraud</li> <li>Electronic Forgery</li> <li>Misuse of Electronic systems and Devices</li> <li>Unauthorized access to code</li> <li>Misuse of Encryption</li> <li>Malicious Code</li> <li>Cyber Stalking</li> <li>Spamming</li> <li>Spoofing</li> <li>Unauthorized interception</li> <li>Cyber Terrorism</li> </ul> <p>The ordinance also describes the prosecution and trail of the offences. It establishes a specialized investigation and prosecution cell within the Federal Investigation Agency (FIA). It also makes ISP’s liable to store traffic data for minimum period of ninety-days. Moreover, forms an Information communication Technologies Tribunal. Prevention of Electronic Crimes Act, 2016 Third IT-related legislation of Pakistan was passed by the parliament in 2016. It follows up on Prevention of Electronic Crimes Ordinance, 2007. This act adds provisions to gain access to data if investigation officers are able to satisfy the court. Also, allows the blocking of unlawful online content. Moreover, the act also adds some new offences and carries some old ones used in the original ordinance. Some new offences it added are as follows:</p> <ul> <li>Hate Speech</li> <li>Recruitment, funding and planning of terrorism</li> <li>Unauthorized issuance of SIM cards</li> <li>Tampering of communication equipment</li> <li>Offences against dignity of a natural person</li> <li>Offences against modesty of a natural person and minor</li> <li>Child pornography</li> </ul> <h2 id="national-cyber-security-policy-2021">National Cyber Security Policy 2021</h2> <p>This policy was drafted as a part of digital Pakistan initiative. It was released in 2021 and its aim is to set a course for better security laws. The vision of the policy is for the country to attain continuously improving digital ecosystem which is secure, robust and ensures confidentiality. The policy reviews the cyber security laws and deems them to be ineffective at protecting citizens of Pakistan for online crimes. It then continues on to describe the challenges and risks faced by Pakistan.</p> <p>This policy is set out to ensure national level corporation between various different government agencies. To improve security of all IT products and create awareness in the country. Furthermore, it aims to train more cyber security professionals. It sets out various principles which must be followed. It then goes on to establish a new committee known as the Cyber Governance Policy Committee and provides an institutional structure for implementation of the policy.</p> <p>It also lists some actions the stakeholders to should take to ensure active defense. Mandates protection of national critical infrastructure and government information systems. Furthermore, it sets out an information security assurance framework.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Pakistan as a country seems to be always 10 to 15 years behind the latest trends. Unfortunatly, this is also the case in the cyber security domain. ThinkTanks of pakistan must focus on these latest trends. Then only Pakistan as a nation can move forwards.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="report"/><category term="reviews"/><category term="technology"/><category term="pakistan"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stay up-to-date on cyber security in Pakistan with this comprehensive report covering the Electronic Transaction Ordinance, Prevention of Electronic Crimes Ordinance and Act, and the National Cyber Security Policy. Learn about the crimes and punishments defined by each legislation, as well as the actions and initiatives outlined in the National Cyber Security Policy]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review of Banda KM-99 Keyboard</title><link href="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Ordering-From-Daraz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review of Banda KM-99 Keyboard"/><published>2022-12-25T18:40:16+05:00</published><updated>2022-12-25T18:40:16+05:00</updated><id>https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Ordering-From-Daraz</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/Ordering-From-Daraz/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently needed a new keyboard as I finally decided to use a desk to work on my laptop. I needed a good keyboard that was durable and also easy to use. So, as anyone in the 21st century would and searched the internet for my options. A leading online marketplace here in Pakistan is daraz.pk. They have a good reputation and have been around since 2012. <a href="https://similarweb.com/top-websites/pakistan/category/e-commerce-and-shopping/">According to simiarweb, it is ranked as the #1 eCommerce platform in Pakistan</a>.</p> <p>Something instantly caught my eye on “daraz.pk” was a product priced at PKR1,997. Its price was slightly higher than the rest of the products. However, this keyboard had the best reviews of them all. The reviews were overwhelmingly positive. It also had a lot of reviews compared to the other products listed. <a href="https://www.daraz.pk/products/i217655853-s1861008808.html?urlFlag=true&amp;mp=1&amp;spm=spm%3Da2a0e.order_details.item_title.1">Here is the link to the Banda KM-99 keyboard i ordered from Daraz.pk</a></p> <h2 id="purchase-decision">Purchase Decision</h2> <p>They listing not only offered a keyboard, but it also offered a mouse along with a free mouse pad. Furthermore, they keyboard had RGB lighting, which is useful in the dark and I think it looks cool. Another prominent feature of this keyboard is that it is spill resistant so it will be able to withstand any accidents. The product was advertised well and<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8KHLWmCyXxs&amp;ab_channel=FunBug">there was even a video showing off the product</a>.</p> <p>There is always doubt when buying products online, so I was still skeptical. However, I decided to continue due to the overwhelming positive. Because it was rated 4.6 / 5 by 1089 shoppers; 891 gave it 5 stars. Plus the seller, Funbug, also has a positive seller rating of 92%. These factors increased my confidence in the product and after much deliberation, I decided to order it. You can check out its specifications on the product page by clicking here.</p> <h2 id="ordering-process">Ordering Process</h2> <p>It stated i would get it on 25th December. Which was only 4 days of shipping time. I generally hate waiting a long time for somthing this is why a major reason why I aviod online shopping. The shipping was the responsibility of daraz as stated on the product page. Daraz has gotten so much better overtime and now have their delivery network all over country. Daraz showed their effienctecy by delivering the product a day earlier, on 24th Dec, then the promised date. “So far so smooth” i thought to myself as i signed for the package and the delivery drive drove off.</p> <h2 id="unboxing">Unboxing</h2> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/thank_you_note-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/thank_you_note-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/thank_you_note-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/thank_you_note.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of the ThankYou note i got with the product" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/box_front-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/box_front-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/box_front-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/box_front.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of the box from the back of the product" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/info_box_back-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/info_box_back-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/info_box_back-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/info_box_back.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of the box from the back of the banda km 99" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Once you open the package you are greeted by a thank-you note. </div> <p>Overall, it was a pretty good unboxing experience. The package was packed neatly. Upon opening the box, you are greeted with a thank you note which is a nice touch. Also, one thing I noticed is that the mouse on the box is not the same one we get. Regardless, I still liked the mouse Funbug gave with the keyboard.</p> <h2 id="product-review">Product Review</h2> <p>The keyboard and mouse are simple to use. All you have to do is plug their USB ports into your pc and they should work right away. The keyboard has a nice feel to it. Pressing the keys feels nice to press and is soft but firm. Pulling on the keys they don’t come off easily and are sturdy. I have not experienced any lag nor did I feel that a key didn’t work.</p> <h3 id="highlights">Highlights</h3> <p>LED Backlight</p> <p>The backlights work just as advertised. They are red on the left, green in the middle, and blue on the right. They are turned on or off by pressing the scroll lock button. They only have an on or off function. It would have been nice to have a blinking and/or cycle option. One unusual thing is that the backlights are attached to the scroll lock feature. Sometimes some apps disable the scroll lock preventing you from using the backlight until you are on that application.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20bright-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20bright-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20bright-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20bright.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of Banda KM 99 With its LED Lights on during dark enviorment" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20light%201-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20light%201-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20light%201-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/keyboard%20led%20light%201.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of Banda KM 99 With its LED Lights on during lit enviorment" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> As you can see they keyboard is illuminated very well by the led backlight </div> <p>Spill Reistance</p> <p>The keyboard had two tiny holes at the back. I assume these are for draining any liquid that falls on it. While I’m afraid to spill anything on the keyboard, it is nice to know that it can survive the spill.</p> <p>The Mouse</p> <p>The mouse is a decent addition. The clicks feel well, and the scroll wheel feels nice. The mouse is accurate and tracks movement pretty decently. The mouse also has LEDs that cycle through colors. There is no way to stop cycling or change the pattern. Unfortunately, you can’t even turn off the led lights. I have to say this mouse does look more incredible in person than it does in pictures.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mouse-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mouse-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mouse-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mouse.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Picture of mouse that we get in this bundle" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="the-mouse-pad">The Mouse Pad</h3> <p>The mouse pad was a gift. Mine is orange; however, according to the product page, it could be different for you. The mouse works well on it, and the mouse feels nice. My conclusion on the mouse pad is that it’s definitely usable but I would get a more premium one.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mousepad-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mousepad-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mousepad-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blogs/2022-12-25-Ordering-From-Daraz/mousepad.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="picture of the mouse pad that is given for free with this product" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="the-cons">The cons</h2> <p>This keyboard feels soo good; however, it is pertinent to note that it is still a membrane keyboard. I feel like the title on the product page can be a little misleading. The RGB lights only have an on-off function and can be toggled using the scroll lock button. Moreover, the QR Codes on the box doesn’t work. One of them leads you to a spam page. So I would suggest you aviod scaning them. The mouse pad is sub-par, so I would just get another one.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>The Banda KM-99 keyboard is a solid choice for the price. The mouse gifted along with it is also pretty decent. While I do not prefer the mouse-pad it will not prevent me from recommending this product. The keyboard looks beautiful, the key presses are soft, and there is minimal lag. I feel elated while typing on this keyboard and have no doubt that it will serve me well for years to come.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="reviews"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking for an in-depth review of the Banda KM 99 keyboard? Our review covers everything from build quality to key feel to lighting effects, helping you make an informed decision on whether the KM 99 is the right keyboard for you]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Blog</title><link href="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/My-First-Blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Blog"/><published>2022-12-11T18:40:16+05:00</published><updated>2022-12-11T18:40:16+05:00</updated><id>https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/My-First-Blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://waleedk2000.github.io/blog/2022/My-First-Blog/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="done-with-the-setup">Done with the setup</h2> <p>I have just finished setting up this website. I feel very exhasted and learned a lot.. phew. Now i’m making my first blog. I used jekyll to built this website. Jekyll is a static website generator. <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/s">You can get jerkyll from here</a>. Just follow the steps on their website or watch this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g6AJ9qPPoyc&amp;ab_channel=SpencerPao">amazing youtube video</a> to get started.</p> <h3 id="tools-used-in-this-website">Tools used in this Website</h3> <ul> <li>Jerkyll</li> <li>Github Pages</li> <li>Git</li> </ul> <h2 id="website-hosting">Website Hosting</h2> <p>This website is hosted on github pages and deploys automatically when i push to remote repository. You can even checkout some of my amazing work on github by visiting the repository section. I’ll be going throught trying to put up my projects as soon as i get some time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general"/><category term="random"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Looking forward to writing many many more]]></summary></entry></feed>